so now let's look at what Loop unrolling
gives us the first benefit it gives us
is that it reduces the overall number of
instructions we have to execute we
started out with this code and the
overall number of instructions that we
execute in a, iterations that we had of
this Loop and the number of instructions
that we had to execute in this Loop was
five instructions in each iteration
times 1,000 iterations of the loop for a
total of 5,000 instructions to do this
Loop now we unroll this Loop once and
got this now the number of instructions
is 8 times in each iteration of this
Loop we are doing the work of two
iterations and we are moving the pointer
by two places so we will only have 500
iterations as opposed to 1,000 here
which gives us only 4,000 instructions
to do the loop instead of 5,000 so we
have atically reduce the number of
instructions it takes to do the loop and
we did it by eliminating What's called
the looping overhead basically this is
the work of the iteration and this is
the looping overhead to go to the next
iteration when we do two iterations at
the time we do twice the work but the
overhead only applies to one of the new
iterations so we get half the overhead
per original iteration remember the iron
law where the execution time is the
number of instructions
times the CPI times the cycle time of
the processor the cycle time will not
change we still have the same processor
the CPI may or may not change but
definitely we have reduced the number of
instructions so we can see that Loop and
rolling just by eliminating the looping
overhead can reduce the execution time
but let's look what happens to the CPI